# Ed Summers ehs@pobox.com / 240-478-7086 304 Brewster Court, Silver Spring, MD 20901

I am a software developer and researcher with two decades of experience bridging the worlds of data management and the Web. I have worked in academia, startups, corporations and government. I accelerate the work of agile, highly collaborative teams that focus on knowledge sharing and a commitment to sustainability.

### Skills

- web technology: APIs, REST, linked data, web archiving
- languages: Python, JavaScript, Ruby, PHP, Perl, Go, Java, C, Scheme
- data analysis: Pandas, SciPy, Spark, Presto
- infrastructure: Linux, AWS, Ansible, Terraform
- databases: PostgreSQL, MariaDB, Redis, ElasticSearch, Solr, MongoDB
- visualization: D3, Plotly, vis.js, Gephi
- practice: agile, automated testing, continuous integration, standards

# Work History

Research Faculty

Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities

University of Maryland

08/2014 - Present

- Full stack software development (JavaScript, React, Python, PostgreSQL, ElasticSearch)
- Social media data analysis and visualization (Python, JavaScript, D3, VisJS)
- Linked Data publishing (Python, NodeJS)
- Sustainable data preservation workflows (AWS)
- Automated testing and continuous integration (GitHub)
- Configuration management (Git, Docker, Ansible)
- Agile requirements gathering & project management
- Instructor & Mentor: software development (Python, JavaScript), data science (Python, Pandas, Spark)

### Consultant

The Brookings Institution

Washington, DC

June 2021 - September 2021

- Social media data collection and ETL (Twitter, Reddit, Python)
- Network analysis and visualization (Python, React, vis.js)
- Report writing and research data publishing

### Visiting Researcher

National Institute of Standards and Technology

Gaithersburg, Maryland

August 2018 - August 2021

- Conducted a multi-year field study to analyze data acquisition methods used in building the world's largest public archive of computer software (NSRL).
- Software development and research design for data data preservation packaging formats (Python, Git, Jupyter, PostgreSQL, BagIt, DFXML, OCFL)

Information Technology Specialist Library of Congress

Washington, DC

03/2006 - 08/2014

- Digital preservation and repository software design and development (Python, Java, MySQL)
- Lead software developer on the National Digital Newspaper Project (Django, MySQL)
- Created a web based quality assurance tool for handling high volume image digitization projects
- Social media archiving (Twitter)
- Designed and implemented the Library of Congress Linked Data Service
- Specification writing and testing W3C

#### Consultant

George Washington University Washington, DC 10/2013 - 12/2014

- Django Web Development
- Voyager ILS integration (Oracle)
- Serial Solutions Summon API integration

#### Consultant

Nelson Institute for Environmental Studies Madison, WI 09/2013 - 06/2014

- Web data harvesting (Python)
- Data packaging and publishing (Git, AWS)

#### Consultant

Hypothes.is San Francisco, CA 01/2013 - 10/2013

- JavaScript and Python development
- Development of the open source Annotator and Annotator Store projects
- Design and implementation of [cross format annotation] annotation support
- Functional/unit testing (Selenium, Pytest, Travis-CI, SauceLabs)

#### Consultant

GlueJar

Montclair, NJ 11/2011 - 04/2012

- Django software development
- AWS (EC2, RDS, Route 53)
- Google Books API harvesting
- Google, Facebook, Twitter social media integration
- Automated testing and continuous integration (Jenkins)

#### Consultant

Yale School of Medicine New Haven, CT 07/2005 - 12/2005

- Python object oriented design
- Automated testing
- Implemented a reporting framework
- Quixote, Pylucene, MySQL, Red Hat administration

Senior Software Engineer

Follett Corporation

McHenry IL

07/2002 - 03/2006

• Web service design and implementation

- Java, PHP and Perl software development
- Automated testing and performance tuning
- Database administration (Oracle, SQL Server)
- XML metadata harvesting and ingest
- Requirements gathering and project planning

#### Consultant

Performix Chicago IL 02/2004 - 04/2005

- Object oriented design
- Refactored large Perl codebase
- Perl, Apache, mod perl, DB2

#### Consultant

Queens Borough Public Library New York, NY 06/2004 - 05/2005

- Character encoding conversion
- Controlled vocabulary mining
- Perl data processing training

### Consultant

Notre Dame University South Bend IN 06/2004 - 12/2004

- Training in object oriented programming and unit testing
- High volume metadata harvesting
- Guidance and implementation search technologies
- Ported Java Common Query Language parser to Perl

## Senior Software Engineer

CheetahMail

New York NY

02/2000 - 07/2002

- Team lead in a group of 8 programmers
- Developed data processing infrastructure for Fortune 500 clients
- Designed/developed real time reporting system
- Creation and maintenance of web service API
- Expertise in SMTP and HTTP protocols
- Web services development
- Technical representative for partners and sales
- Networking and systems administration as required

## Metadata Specialist

Old Dominion University

Norfolk, VA

04/1998 - 02/2000

- SGML and XML data processing for the VIVA Consortium
- Created current awareness system to alert students/faculty to new items in their field of interest.
- ILS and OCLC metadata workflow management

Visiting Assistant Professor University of Illinois

Champaign-Urbana, IL

08/1996 - 03/1998

- Web development (ASP, SQL Server)
- Collection development and cataloging in Sociology and Political Science
- Preservation of 19th century criminology pamphlet collection
- Managed reference services in the Social Science Library

# Selected Projects

These are some projects and experiments where I've been directly involved in the technical development.

- Unlocking the Airwaves NEH funded virtual reunification and minimal computing project
- Documenting the Now Mellon funded social media archiving practices and tools
- Chronicling America Library of Congress access to historical newspapers.
- Linked Data Service Publishing controlled vocabularies at the Library of Congress using Linked Data
- Hypothesis An annotation tool for the web
- Wikistream visualize realtime edits to all major language Wikipedias
- Anon track anonymous Wikipedia edits using Twitter
- Pymarc a python library for MARC processing
- jobs.code4lib.org a jobs board for the code4lib community
- Linkypedia view how websites are used on Wikipedia
- Fondz generate an archival description for describing born digital content
- Microdata a python library for parsing HTML 5 microdata
- rdflib a Python library for processing RDF

## **Selected Publications**

- Legibility Machines: Archival Appraisal and the Genealogies of Use. PhD Dissertation. University of Maryland. December, 2020.
- Appraisal Talk in Web Archives. Archivaria. May, 2020.
- Archival Circulation on the Web: The Vine-Tweets Dataset. Cultural Analytics. June, 2019.
- Algorithms and Agenda-Setting in Wikileaks' #PodestaEmails Release. Information, Communication & Society. 2019
- Appraisal Practices in Web Archives. SocArXiv Papers, 2018.
- Twitter and Tear Gas: Book Review. Internet Histories, 2017.
- Ferguson and the death of Michael Brown on Twitter: #BlackLivesMatter, #TCOT, and the evolution of collective identities. Ethnic and Racial Studies, 40(10).
- #sayhername: a case study of intersectional social media activism. Ethnic and Racial Studies, 40(10).
- Bots, Seeds and People: Web Archives as Infrastructure. Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing, CSCW 17.
- Automating Transparency. The Source. April, 2015.
- MJ no more: Using Concurrent Wikipedia Edit Spikes with Social Network Plausibility Checks for Breaking News Detection. 2013.
- Linking Things on the Web: A Pragmatic Examination of Linked Data, 2013.
- Key Choices in the Design of Simple Knowledge Organization System (SKOS), 2013.
- Library Linked Data Final Report, W3C Incubator Group Report, October 2011.
- SKOS Simple Knowledge Organization System Primer, W3C Working Group Note, August 18th, 2008. http://www.w3.org/TR/skos-primer/
- LCSH, SKOS and Linked Data, Proceedings of the International Conference on DublinCore and Metadata Applications, 2008.
- Following Your Nose to the Web of Data, Information Standards Quarterly, 2008
- Building OAI-PMH Harvesters With Net::OAI::Harvester Ariadne, no. 38, Jan 2004.
- Cyril: Expanding the Horizons of MARC21, Library Hi Tech, v. 22, no. 1, 2004.
- A Consortial Approach to Cooperative Cataloging and Authority Control: The Virtual Library of Virginia Experience, Resource Sharing and Information Networks, v. 16, no. 1, 2003, p. 33-53.
- Paying Homage to Perl (PHP), The Perl Review, January, 2003.
- MARC it your way: MARC.pm, Information Technology and Libraries, March, 2002.

- Comprehensive Access to Periodicals: A Database Solution, Library Collections Acquisitions and Technical Services, v. 24, no. 2, 2000, p. 33-44.
- Chaos-Show Me the Metadata, Against the Grain, v.11, no.1, 1998.
- Gateways to Social Work/Welfare on the Net, C&RL News, v.59, no. 3, 1998, p.163-167.

## Education

- PhD, College of Information Studies, University of Maryland, 2015-2020.
- MLS, School of Communications, Information and Library Science, Rutgers University, 1995-1996.
- BA English and American Literature, Rutgers University, 1987-1991.

## Awards

- 2018 Community Capacity Award. Digital Library Federation.
- 2018 Exemplary Service Award. Society of American Archivists.
- 2015 University of Maryland Scholarship and Research Award
- 2015 Frederick G. Kilgour Award for Research in Library and Information Technology. American Library Association.